warning sodium cyanide is an extremely
toxic poison this experiment must be
performed with gloves in a fume hood
this experiment also uses high
temperatures a fire safety protocols
must be in place this should only be
performed by experienced chemist now
seriously this is some crazy-ass weasel
if you screw up you will die I'm
not joking around here the only reason
why I am doing this is because it's
necessary to make the drug pure methane
if you do not possess at least a
bachelor's degree in chemistry do not
try this doing it is straightforward but
staying safe required a safety mentality
that you can only get with actual lab
experience
seriously don't try this greetings
fellow nerds in this video we're going
to make sodium cyanide while it is
famous as lethal poison it is
tremendously useful in chemistry to
manufacture other chemicals like
nitriles in fact the reason why it
became so famous as a poison is because
it's used so much in the industry that's
easy to access and get poisoned in both
accidentally and intentionally but there
are plenty of other even more toxic
chemicals but they aren't used enough to
become as well known as cyanide
I'll be using sodium cyanide to make a
nitrile compound for making pure
methanol now we're going to need
moderately high temperatures for this so
we're going to modify our heating mantle
we made in earlier video rather than
wrapping around a flask we're going to
wrap it around a steel can I'm using a
steel can and not a beaker because we're
going to melt sweet hydroxide later
molten sodium hydroxide eats through
glass so we have to use a metal can
instead my heating tape is falling apart
because I accidentally heat it beyond
the insulators max and temperature it's
still good for another use but I'm
buying a new tape soon for safety my
fume hood stands and other metal
connections are grounded anyway here is
the fully assembled unit it's darker in
color than earlier because I was doing
some heating as well as grounding test
to make sure it was safe to use let me
switch over to overhead camera since
looking at it from the side is boring
now the star we add 100
grams of solid rock side then we add 43
grams of cyanuric acid which is sold as
a chlorine stabilizer swimming pools
finally we add 12 grams of carbon now
give the mixture a good stir and slowly
ramp up the temperature to 600 Celsius
don't eat the mixture too fast roll
sputter go slowly over the course of an
hour as it starts to liquify
occasionally stir to make sure there are
no cold spots as temperature increases
the mixture may start to bubble this is
to be expected
first the cyanuric acid and sodium
hydroxide will react to form try sodium
sign aerated water at these temperatures
the water will boil off then as the
mixture reaches 550 Celsius the
trisodium cyanuric decomposes into
sodium cyanide this then reacts with
carbon to form carbon dioxide and sodium
cyanide some carbon dioxide will bubble
out but some will react with the same
hydroxide to make sodium carbonate there
should be constant bubbling if the
bubbling goes too fast and threatens to
overflow the heating mantle then turn
down the temperature to get back under
control
eventually the bubbling should slow down
and we can start raising the temperature
again once we reach citrate Celsius
without overflow we continued heating
for another hour the bubbling should
eventually stop then we turn off the
heating let the mixture cool now rather
than sign uric acid urea can also be
used to make cyanide as at high
temperatures it reacts with hydroxides
to produce ammonia and cyanate this can
then react with carbon to make cyanide
as usual now we have our cooled mixture
of sodium cyanide sodium cyanide
symud Rock sides sodium carbonate and
leftover carbon to separate them we have
to get them all out - and sold them in
methanol the mixture is very hard like
rocks so I add the methanol directly to
it to soften and gradually break it up
and scoop it out once again I must
emphasize you wear gloves and have
safety precautions because this is a
highly toxic solution of methanol and
cyanide so here is our mixture of
methanol sodium cyanide and various
byproducts and side products stir it up
to break up the chunks to a fine powder
and dissolve as much of the sodium
cyanide as possible I found I had to add
more methanol to a total volume of 5
milli
because the solution was becoming
somewhat difficult to start now once all
this hard material has been reduced to a
fine powder continue stirring and start
adding 100 grams of sodium bicarbonate
add in small portions slowly doesn't
clump up into chunks what we're doing is
reacting the sodium bicarbonate with
some hydroxide hadn't confirmed sodium
carbonate sodium carbonate has low
solubility in methanol well sodium
hydroxide has high solubility so by
converting the submerged rock excited to
sodium carbonate it can be precipitated
out and separate from the sodium cyanide
after all these Summa carburetors added
let the mixture stir for about half an
hour and now we filter the mixture and
here is our methanol solution of sodium
cyanide there is a small amount of very
fine carbon dust and sodium carbonate
and bicarbonate we can easily filter
that again before we go further we
should test to make sure we really do
have cyanide here's a fresh prepared
solution of ferrous sulfate it's very
little only about maybe half the gram in
10 milliliters of water now we add a few
drops of the solution of cyanide and
methanol to the ferrous sulphate
solution what we're trying to make the
substance called Prussian blue which has
a deep blue color but Prussian blue
requires both iron 3 and iron 2 ions
since the solution of ferrous sulfate
fresh it only has iron 2 to create some
iron 3 ions I just add in a few drops of
hydrogen peroxide let me give it a shake
there we go something is happening let
me add it in a few more drops of the
cyanide solution there we go it's a very
strong blue color this is the pigment
Russian blue and this proves that we
have cyanide ions so now I fill trail
one more time to get rid of the very
fine particles and then I remove the
methanol by boiling it off I'm
distilling here because I want to reuse
the methanol for future runs and because
I want to reduce the air exposure they
are actually reacts with cyanide to
convert the harm of cyanide and here's
our dried sodium cyanide it's a bit
impure with some sodium carbonate but it
should be good enough for amateur uses
and here it is transferred to some vials
my total yield was about 19 grams this
yield is about 36% based on the sign
Eric acid I can probably improve the
yield by heating for longer dissolving
the survivor oxide and cyanuric acid
together in water first and then drying
and maybe using potassium hydroxide
instead swim hydroxide because the
decomposition temperature of potassium
cyanide is lower than sodium cyanide and
well considering how cheap the reagents
are I don't mind low yield as I can just
try again on larger scale to get warm
I'm going to be using sodium cyanide to
dissolve gold and doogle playing
experiments and I'll be using its
precursor to make the drug pure Metheny
know the irony you've used an extremely
lethal poison to make a life-saving drug
is not lost on me
but chemistry is amazing like that oh
yes a word of note on waste disposal
before toss them out or washing them to
soak the beakers flasks filter papers
and whatever else touch cyanide in
liquid chlorine bleach for a few days
these same epiclloyd a the bleached
oxides a cyanide in relatively harmless
cyanide thanks for watching if you would
like to support the continued production
of science videos like this one please
support the channel on patreon links are
in the video description
you